If you drink coffee, I'll bet you no
money, because I have no money to bet
that you've never heard of these effects
that it has on your cardiovascular
system and your heart. I ran across a
fascinating study going into some
serious depth on the effects of
chlorogenic acid, a powerful polyphenol
molecule found in coffee. We'll go over
the data, describe the mechanisms, and
then sum it up together at the end. The
study, this one, is a mechanism study to
understand what happens when exposed to
coffeey's chlorogenic acid. The crux of
the study is to use four groups of mice.
One control group given nothing, another
two groups given chlorogenic acid at a
low and high concentration, and a final
group known as a positive control given
a statin, which is a lipid blood
cholesterol lowering drug. The unique
aspects of these mice is the fact that
they're APOE null mice. Meaning the APOE
gene has been removed from these mice,
which means that they develop heart
disease at a much quicker rate because
the APOE protein found in the particles
that carry cholesterol throughout our
body are less able to be cleared from
the bloodstream leading to significant
accumulation and arterial plaque
formation. So the researchers took
measurements of arterial plaque, blood
panels, inflammatory markers, and things
like aortic dilotation. So I'll explain
what that is. Let's start with looking
at the plaque levels. Remember plaque is
filled with these lipoprotein particles
that are trapped under a layer of cells
called endothelial cells. So the greater
deposition and oxidation or modification
of these particles leads to more plaque
growth. Fascinatingly, if we look at
these data on plaque size, we see that
the control condition is on the left
side. That is what we're comparing
against. The ator of a statin is the
statin the lipid lowering drug and the
two pink conditions on the right are the
chlorogenic acid conditions. Clearly, we
can see that all three conditions show
reduced plaque in the arteries compared
to the control, indicating that the
statin and the chlorogenic acid reduce
plaque burden in the artery wall, which
is really fascinating. There's more that
we'll need to say on this later, but for
now, let's go into even more of this
interesting finding. There's another
problem that comes from atheroscerosis,
the uh plaque buildup, and that's aortic
dilotation. Essentially, as plaque
builds up in your aorta, which is a
section branching from the heart, and in
this section, if it accumulates with
plaque, also attracts immune cells that
infiltrate into the plaque region. In
doing so, these immune cells release a
series of molecules called cytoines that
not only attract more immune cells to
the region, but they also inc can
encourage the release of degradation
proteins called MMPs. These MMPs degrade
the surrounding structure of the aorta,
weakening it. This also happens in other
areas of the vascule. It's just that the
aorta is especially deadly. So if the
integrity is degraded it makes the aorta
stiffer because the elastin proteins get
destroyed that is measured by dilotation
which indicates ballooning or abnormal
enlargement of the blood vessel. Looking
at the data we can see that the statin
and the greatest dose of chlorogenic
acid reduced aortic dilotation
indicating a positive effect. Now that
might be due to the reduction in plaque
volume or it may be through some other
mechanism. But regardless, chlorogenic
acid seems to help. Okay, so we've been
pretty focused on reduced plaque size
and the offshoot effects that might
have. But what is leading to this
atherosclerosis improvement?
Fortunately, the researchers did an
elegant experiment where they
fluorescently labeled cholesterol
molecules to track cholesterol movement.
This cholesterol is called NBD
cholesterol. Then they applied
chlorogenic acid to macrofasages. These
are the primary immune cells that drive
themselves into the plaque and
contribute to the instability and growth
of the plaque. That instability is due
to these macrofasages which are trying
to help are consuming large amounts of
cholesterol in an attempt to eliminate
them from being trapped in the plaque
and in so doing get laden with
cholesterol which leads them to form
into foam cells. One way to avoid this
instability as well as potentially
reverse plaque in the artery is to
remove cholesterol molecules. The way
that is done is through cholesterol elux
which is mediated by another set of
particles called HDL or highdensity
lipoproteins. HDL doesn't get trapped
like other particles. So it can pick up
cholesterol molecules and drop them off
at the liver to be eliminated. That's
cholesterol e-lux and reverse
cholesterol transport at work. So what
happens to cholesterol elux to these HDL
particles? Well, it increases
conditionally. We have our trusty
control condition here. And remember,
the higher the bar, the greater the
cholesterol e-lux, a good thing. The
CGA1 and the CGA10 are the chlorogenic
acid conditions. And we can clearly see
they indicate increased cholesterol
e-lux. But that last condition with the
GW there does not. Why? While scientists
are often curious to test if they were
to block a particular cellular pathway
if it would have an effect on the result
that they're seeing. In this situation
they're adding
GW9662 which is an inhibitor of a master
protein found in our cells called par
gamma. Par gamma is a protein that
encourages the expression of many genes
some of which seem to be involved in
cholesterol e-lux from the immune cells.
If we block par gamma cholesterol e-lux
no longer occurs and on top of that the
resigly condition there is resiglatazone
uh par gamma activator and we see a
robust el-lux of cholesterol to HDL
indicating that pathway alone can lead
to cholesterol elux. Now before we
continue with a few warnings that PER
gamma angle that we just discussed
actually continues with more on the
mechanisms of how it works inside the
cells to lead to cholesterol elux and
there are some other ways that
chlorogenic acid helps our body avoid
cardiovascular disease. If you're
interested in more I'm covering that in
the full version of the video that
you're watching that's included with the
Physiotic Insiders along with podcasts,
live sessions with me, a library of
these kinds of videos, research reviews,
and more. It's a great way to continue a
detailed education on how your body
works and what to do to improve it. The
link to join is in the description box.
I'd love to have you there. But there
are some considerations to keep in mind
here. One, this is a pre-clinical data.
It's not like I suddenly went insane and
lost my sense of scientific order of
operations. These kinds of data don't
speak to the applicable information. But
before you comment mean comments on what
the point of the video is, I'll bring it
back to you and me, unless you're a
mouse, in which case this already
applies pretty well. Two, a bit in the
same neighborhood, chlorogenic acid
doses given the in these studies are
much higher than that found in coffee.
So again, beyond the fact that this is
in mice, the effect sizes will likely be
smaller in humans. Okay, sobering
caveats out of the way, does that mean
that we wasted our time here? No, first
I got to annoy you with some wickedly
cool science. But beyond my egoentrism,
there are some human trials using
chlorogenic acid. And although not
plentiful, the few randomized control
trials using chlorogenic acid do
indicate benefit. But beyond that,
chlorogenic acid is a major molecule in
coffee. And there are many studies that
indicate a relationship between coffee
consumption and reduced cardiovascular
disease risk. It seems reasonable
considering all these data that
chlorogenic acid in that addictive dark
liquid is playing a role in that
protective process. So where does that
leave us? It's pretty simple. Coffee is
a healthy drink that likely works
through at least partly chlorogenic acid
in protecting us from cardiovascular
disease. So if you're drinking coffee,
good for you. If not, here's a reason to
start considering the totality of
evidence. But just because you drink it
doesn't mean that you couldn't improve
its effects by doing what I mentioned
here.